Hello, everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and
today we're talking about
an uncomfortable subject, not because it's
uncomfortable to talk
about, but because it's, well,
it doesn't really feel good
when you have to go do it.
That's right. Today we're going to
the doctor, but because we need to get
vaccines. Alright, so vaccines, these are
well, let's listen out during the
dialogue and maybe you can guess
what this word means when
we come back, we'll be defining
it for you, talking about
different kinds of vaccines.
But just remember that we're talking about
going to the doctor to get these shots.
So let's take a listen to that dialogue.
Hello, Mrs. Parker. How have you been?
Hello, Dr. Peters. Just fine. Thank you.
Ricky and I are here for his vaccines.
Very well. Let's see. According to his
vaccination record, Ricky has received
his polio, tetanus, and hepatitis B shots.
He is 14 months old, so he is due for
hepatitis A, chicken pox, and measles shots.
What about rubella and mumps? Well, I can
only give him knees for now, and after a
couple of weeks, I can administer the rest.
Okay, great. Dr. I think I also may need
a tetanus booster. Last time I got it
was maybe 15 years ago. We'll check our
records and I'll have
the nurse administer
the booster as well. Now,
please hold Ricky's arm tight.
This may sting a little. All right,
we're back. So now let's take a look
at all of these words.
They're a little bit difficult,
but we'll try to define
them on language takeaway.
So, Marco, first off,
what is a vaccine?
So, a vaccine we can say
is a type of medicine, but
it's basically an injection
or medicine where
you're helping a person defend him or
herself against a specific type of disease.
Okay, so vaccination is
medicine you receive before
your sick so that in the future, you won't
get sick with that disease. That's right.
That's right. So, that's a vaccine. There
are many, many different types of vaccines.
And of course, when
you do get them, you
need to keep track of them
via a vaccination record.
So, a record is basically a list or a
document that shows what has been done.
And this is very important
when you go to the doctor
to have a record of the things that you
have received, the vaccines you've received.
So, for example, if I have
a baby and I want the
baby to have vaccinations, we'd have to
keep a record of all of his vaccinations.
That's right. So, we
are obviously, we get
different vaccines at
different stages in our life.
Let's talk about some of the ones
that we're taking a look at today.
So, for example, we have a
tetanus vaccine or a tetanus shot.
All right. The tetanus
shot is very famous
because it's maybe
the most painful. It really
makes you soar for a little while. And most
people get the tetanus shot when they're
very young. This
prevents you from getting
the disease tetanus.
And tetanus is something
you can get from
animals or from dirty nails,
dirty metal, anything
that that pokes out at you.
And so, you get the tetanus shot, but then,
after your tetanus shot, every five or ten
years, you need to
get a booster shot.
So, there's the tetanus shot
and there's the tetanus booster.
So, when we talk about a booster when we're
talking about vaccines is basically you are
reinforcing it. You
are making it stronger
because obviously, over
time, it becomes weak.
The medicine won't last forever.
So, you need to get a booster to
make sure that you are still protected.
Basically, it's an
update. That's right.
So, we have tetanus
and tetanus booster, but
we have another kind of vaccine.
The disease here is called hepatitis.
That's right. So, we're
taking a look at hepatitis
B and hepatitis A.
So, there are different
types of hepatitis. That's right.
So, both kinds of hepatitis, you can catch
from other people.
Although hepatitis A, I
believe you can catch
from saliva or contact
whereas hepatitis B,
you catch from other
people's blood or if you have
a relationship with someone.
So, hepatitis A and B are different.
Hepatitis B affects your liver.
And so, there's different
kinds of severity here.
Now, hepatitis A and B,
there are vaccinations for.
You can get those shots and
it's very important if you're
traveling to places that require
them so that you don't get sick.
Okay. So, well, these are
different types of hepatitis.
They are dangerous, right?
And they could be fatal.
But another one that's very,
very common, especially
with young kids,
we have chickenpox. Chickenpox. Now, it's
kind of a funny name. Chickenpox, no X.
But it's also, like you say,
very common. So, basically,
the symptoms are what, you get these
red bumps all over your body and they itch.
You want to scratch
and scratch and scratch.
And so, I remember when
I had this, I was a little kid.
My mom said, don't scratch because if
you scratch, it will leave a mark. Right.
It leaves a scar. So,
yeah, chickenpox, you
get these little rashes
all over your body.
They're very itchy. But
they will go away with time.
Now, it's it's usually, I've heard that
it's recommended that people get it.
Actually, you should get it
when you're young because
it's more dangerous if
you get it as an adult.
That's right. It's very
painful as an adult.
So, basically, chickenpox, they say, if
you get it once, you can't get it again.
Right. I'll never get it again. But if
you get it as an adult, it's shingles.
It's very painful. Okay. Very
good. So, we've taken a look
at a lot of vocab here.
Why don't we now jump
to another section
that's continued talking
about these different types of vaccines.
Let's go to language takeaway part two.
All right. So, we have
this special category
of vaccinations. They
usually go together.
We have mumps,
measles, and rubella.
Or, there's a special acronym,
M-M-R, mumps, measles, rubella.
Okay. So, you basically
get like a little combo.
You usually get all
three of them at one go.
So, what are these measles?
All right. Measles.
Well, measles is a virus.
He's got the measles.
You often read books from
like the 19th century
where everyone gets the
measles when they're
a child. But measles is
basically a virus, but
it's kind of like the
chickenpox because you
get a rash on your skin.
And is it fatal? Like, can
you die from the measles?
I think in the old days you could,
but these days it's pretty, pretty easy
to take care of. And
what about mumps?
Now, mumps, I'm not
too sure about this, but I've
heard that mumps is
like a swelling in the space
between your jaw and
your ear. So, you know
where your ear kind of comes down to your
jaw, that part of your head starts to swell
and is very uncomfortable. Right. And it
could cause like the consequences, it could
be fatal, right? Right.
And what about rubella?
Rubella is another kind of rash.
And from my reading, I
saw that rubella is not very
dangerous for most people,
but it is very dangerous
for pregnant women.
So, most pregnant women
are tested for rubella
or the rubella vaccine.
And they're told to
get the vaccine before
they're pregnant so
that they don't get this
disease and harm their
baby because they can
have a miscarriage if they get rubella
while they're pregnant. Right. Right. Okay.
So, pretty much you want
to get all these vaccines
to make sure that you
don't get sick in the future.
Now, when we were
talking about getting
the vaccines, the doctor said, you didn't
say you're going to get the vaccines or I'm
going to give you a
vaccine. He said, I'll have
the nurse administer the
vaccine or administer the booster.
That's right. So, the verb here that
we use with vaccine is too administer.
And this is something
that the nurse does or
the doctor does. And
it's just a way to say
that the nurse will give
you this shot to give
you a shot, but
administer is more formal.
It's more common in the
medical kind of medical talk.
Right. So, you'd say administer
the test or administer the vaccine.
So, for example, a doctor
would say, I'm going to administer
a shot of penicillin. That's right. Or
I'm going to administer this blood test.
That means I'm actually
going to do it right now.
Now, obviously, these vaccines, some
of them you can't take as a little pill.
Some of them you can't
take as drops like, you know,
it's very painless. But
some of them you have
to get a shot and
sometimes they do hurt.
And we saw in the
dialogue that the doctor
said, this may sting a little. Doctors
always say this before they give you a shot.
This may sting a little.
Now, sting is a verb that
means to hurt, but it's
not like I hit you in the face.
Boom, right. Stings.
No, a sting is like a kind of a
very kind of light hurts, like a pinch.
It's like a small, sharp pain.
Small, sharp pain. That's
a good way to describe it.
So, oftentimes
we talk about bees.
You know, bees that fly around, they sting
you. Right. Right. So, it's a small, sharp
pain. Right. Okay, very
good. So, let's listen
to the dialogue
again. Let's keep a look
out for how we pronounce all of
these words and we'll be back in a bit.
Hello, Mrs. Parker.
How have you been?
Hello, Dr. Peters.
Just fine. Thank you.
Ricky and I are here for
his vaccines. Very well.
Let's see. According to
his vaccination record,
Ricky has received
his polio, tetanus, and
hepatitis B shots. He
is 14 litts old, so he
is due for hepatitis A,
chicken pox and measles shots.
What about rubella
and mumps? Well,
I can only give him
bees for now and after a
couple of weeks, I
can administer the rest.
Okay, great. Dr. I
think I also may need a
tetanus booster. Last time I
got it was maybe 15 years ago.
We'll check our records and I'll have
the nurse administer the booster as well.
Now, please hold
Ricky's arm tight.
This may sting a little. So,
nowadays, most of these shots
are administered when
the babies are just born.
They're still in the
hospital and they get
a lot of vaccines and
to prevent them from
getting these things.
That's right. And I remember
when I was a kid,
we didn't even have a
vaccine for chicken
pox. So, these days there
are more and more.
The oldest, I think, is the
polio vaccine, the one
that we hear the most
about because it was a very serious disease
that affected a lot of people up until the
1940s and 50s, I
believe. So, yeah, it's
important really to read
about these things and
to educate yourself so that you know
what you should get yourself and your kids.
That's exactly right
because it's very important.
Most of these diseases or most of these
viruses have been eradicated because more
and more people have
had access to vaccines.
For example, polio,
it's very rare, you would
say, to actually get it nowadays because
there's a vaccine, but it's very, very
important, I think. But
some people get a little
bit too nervous. Like,
for example, whenever
they travel to a tropical country,
they're always afraid of yellow fever.
So, they get yellow fever
shots. But I've never really seen
anyone get yellow fever because
you go to Thailand for a week.
A friend of mine went to
Thailand and got dengue fever.
So, there's no
vaccination for this, but it is
a very painful disease, you
can get in tropical places.
So, I think the moral is talk to your
doctor, see what he or she suggests because
they will understand maybe better than you
will. And then, you know, just follow their
advice for different places
that you're traveling to.
That's right. So, that's all
the time we have for today.
But if you guys
have any questions
or doubts, you can always
visit us at our website www.
EnglishPod.com and
we'll be there to answer it.
Bye, everyone. Bye.
(upbeat music)